成橛钪婀民的粝
The dream of becoming a citizen of the cosmos
在2000年前 Q生於此
was born here, more than two millennia ago,
v山大城
in the city of Alexandria,
@座城市的名字是榱思o念它的征服者
named after and conceived by its dead conqueror,
已去世的v山大大帝
Alexander the Great.
希D的托勒密王朝
The Ptolemys, the Greek kings
^承了v山大帝的埃及地^
who inherited the Egyptian portion of Alexander's empire,
K修建了@座D^
built this library
成立了相P的研究C
and its associated research institution.
可以f @是非常罕的e措
Rarely, if ever,
不H空前 而且^後
before or since,
]有一政府花那N多X
has there been a government that was willing to spend
把家收入的大部分
so much of its gross national product
投入到χR的@取中
on the acquisition of knowledge.
有付出就有回
And it paid off.
知R的大r代砼R了
Big time.
每一艘M入v山大港的船b
Every ship entering Alexandria's harbor
都要M行搜查 查的不是`禁品
was searched-- not for contraband,
而是那些放在船上的籍手抄本
but for books that might be copied and stored here,
lF後就w入@座r世界上最ゴ蟮D^
in what was then the greatest library on Earth.
正是在@Y D^的^L埃拉托斯特尼
Here, Eratosthenes, one of the chief librarians,
蚀_的算出了地球的直
accurately calculated the size of the Earth
K建了地理W
and invented geography.
_哥拉斯
Pythagoras.
希帕蒂I
Hypatia.
W桌锏
Euclid.
W桌锏迷谥作中U述了缀W的定律
Euclid set forth the precepts of geometry
2300年後 他的著作依然被世人使用
in a textbook that remained in use for 2,300 years.
《}?fs》也是倪@Y_始散播到人世
The Old Testament Bible comes down to us
的大部分在@Y被翻g成了希DZ
mainly from the Greek translations made here.
很多ゴ笞髌返脑始手稿也保存在@Y
The original manuscripts of the masterpieces
包括希D的喜  歌
of Greek comedy and drama, poetry,
科W著作 工程著作
science, engineering,
tW著作 v史著作
medicine and history--
失落的古代文明作品被重新拘
the total work product
妥妥的保存在@Y
of the awakening of ancient civilization-- were kept here.
推y @Y的藏
Estimates vary on the total number of scrolls.
大概有50f卷以上
They range from 500,000
甚至多_上百f卷
to nearly a million.
所有的@些作品
And all of it...
所有的@些籍
all of this
F在只需要很小的一空g
is but a tiny fraction of the information
就像你的指尖那N大的地方就可以保存了
that you have at your fingertips at this very moment.
人集w的知R
The collective knowledge of our species,
存在我自己的v山大子D^Y
our own electronic Library of Alexandria,
只要你身上в邢的O 就Sr可以@取
may be accessed by anyone who has a device
你劭词颤N就看什N 什Nr候想看就什Nr候看
and the interest and the freedom to do so.
可在^去的v山大城 @拥氖虑槭遣l生的
This was not true in Alexandria,
知R只凫赌承┚英人士
where knowledge belonged to the elite.
因此在公元前四世o
So in the fourth century AD,
暴民摧D^r
when the mob came to destroy the library
古典文明的精A被摧r
and the genius of classical civilization,
]有什N人站起肀Ｐl它
there were not enough people to defend it.
等下一次的暴y砼Rr 又l生些什N
What will happen the next time the mob comes?
宇宙大探索
第十三集
我已一起v了一段漫L的旅程
We've come a long way together,
我深入了原子的群
traveling from deep inside the heart of an atom
抵_了宇宙的
clear out to the cosmic horizon,
rg的起源走到bh的未
and from the beginning of time to the distant future.
我是r候做一些了
I think we're ready to perform an experiment.
@不是那N在室Y才能做的
It's not the kind of experiment that requires a laboratory.
你可以在自己的X海Y完成它
You can do it in your head.
它Q之"思想"
It's called a "thought experiment."
x一w星星
Pick a star--
就在我的y河系Yx上
any one of the hundreds of billions of stars
@狄园|w星星中的一w
in our Milky Way Galaxy,
其y河系也只不^是
which is just one galaxy
目前已知宇宙的上百|星系中的一
out of the hundred billion in the known universe.
@w怎N
How about that star?
或者是那一w
Or that one?
好 就是@w吧
Okay, this one.
有资行星和l星@著它旋D
It's orbited by dozens of planets and moons.
假O 其中的一w
Suppose, on one of them,
上面有智能生物存在
there lives an intelligent species,
他是@行星Y上千fN生命形式的一N
one the ten million life-forms on that planet,
在@些智能生物中
and there's a subgroup of that species
有一小部分生物J樗已lF了
who believe they have it all figured out--
@世界就是宇宙的中心
their world is the center of the universe,
@宇宙樗而造
a universe made for them,
他已o所不知
and that they know everything they need to know about it--
碛辛AM的智慧
their knowledge is complete.
你X得他的可以真
How seriously would you take their claim?
我的祖先就J
Our ancestors believed
宇宙是樗而造的
the universe was made for them.
把人假定槭澜绲闹行氖呛茏匀坏氖虑
It was natural to assume that we were at the center.
竟 太和其他的星星
After all, it looks like the Sun and stars
看起矶@著人D
all revolve around us.
我F在在f 太是"升"起淼
We still speak of the Sun "rising."
人的Z言 神和粝氲捏w系Y
The architecture of our language, myths and dreams
是碜钥WQ生前的r代
comes from that pre-scientific age.
在哥布出航lF新大前
This is our planet as it was known then,
人都J橐呀很t解@星球了
just before Columbus set sail.
@是世界上第一地球x
This first globe of the Earth was cutting-edge
R丁?海姆在1492年u造了@r是最前沿的a品
when Martin Behaim made it in 1492.
和r的其他人一 他J
Like everyone else, he believed
@幅世界地理的拼D已完整o缺了
that the jigsaw puzzle of geography was complete.
上面有三大
There were three continents...
W洲 非洲和洲
Europe, Africa and Asia,
三大洲之g只有浩瀚的大洋
and only the great world ocean in between.
海姆地球x上看不到北美洲c南美洲的存在
Behaim had no clue that North and South America even existed.
人很容易自以槭 Σ
It's easy to feel smug, right?
事上 R丁?海姆λ的世界的t解
Well, the fact is Martin Behaim knew infinitely more
Φ厍虻牟t解
about his world, the Earth,
hh龠^我於宇宙的t解
than we know about ours, the universe.
近代有一P于t的故事
A recent lesson in humility
可以很好的作槊髯C
will serve to illustrate.
1912年 S克托?赫斯M行了好状物w行
In 1912, Victor Hess made a series of voyages
他w越了W地利上空
into the sky above Austria,
lF了科W家期待已久的|西…
and found the thing that scientists love best...
一神秘而o法理解的事件
a mystery that defied understanding
用鹘y的科Wo法解
in terms of conventional scientific wisdom.
r至今日
And even today,
100年^去了 我仍在苦苦搜
a century later, we are still searching
要楹账沟陌lF找一完整的答案
for a complete explanation of what Hess found.
r有一N新的能量被lF
A new kind of energy had recently been discovered,
射能
radioactivity.
也就是放射能
自然界中某N特定的元素放出射
It was given off
比如D
by certain elements, like radium.
但空庵幸灿休射
But it was also found in the air,
在hx放射性岩石的地方也有射
even far away from radioactive rocks.
它可f是o不在
It was everywhere.
@些奇怪的能量是哪难Y淼
Where did this strange energy come from?
o人知
No one knew.
赫斯推y它可能碜缘厍蛏峡
Hess suspected that it might come from above the Earth.
榱蓑C@假O 他yе射探y器
To test his hypothesis, he carried radiation detectors
w向高空
high into the sky.
他冒著乘坐馇虻娘LU
During a risky ascent in a hydrogen balloon,
他到_了海拔超^3英里的高度
he attained an altitude of more than three miles.
他淼娇庀” 囟群冷的
When he reached the thin, cold,
大又胁恳陨r
upper half of the atmosphere...
他lF@Y的射值
he found that the radiation
比地面的要2倍以上
was more than twice as strong as on the ground.
@些射一定是碜造陡高
The radiation must be coming from above.
因此它在地面才比^弱
That's why its intensity was weaker on the ground--
因榈厍虻拇游收了大部分能量
the Earth's atmosphere was absorbing most of it.
有人J檫@些射可能碜造短
Some thought that the radiation might come from the Sun.
榱y@f法
To test that idea, Hess timed one of his ascents
赫斯在一次日食r升上高空
to coincide with a solar eclipse.
他lF日食射]有任何影
But the eclipse had no effect on the radiation.
赫斯lF
Hess also found that the radiation
射在白天和晚上的度是一拥
was just as strong at night as in daylight.
@些射是碜造陡呖 但不是太
It was coming from above, but not from the Sun.
赫斯不知道
What Hess did not know
太L根本就]有那N快的速度
was that the solar wind doesn't move that quickly.
因此 他And so, for the wrong reason,
做出了正_的Y
he came to the right conclusion.
赫斯lF了宇宙射
Hess had discovered cosmic rays--
那些如雨一般在宇宙中交ew⒌原子粒子
showers of subatomic particles that crisscross the universe
它以光速行M著
at literally the speed of light.
如果]有地球大拥谋Ｗo
Without the shielding effect of the Earth's atmosphere,
它可致人死地
they would be lethal.
某些宇宙射yУ哪芰
Some cosmic rays can carry as much energy
c步中l射的子一
as a bullet fired from a rifle.
人花了资年的rg追宇宙射
It would take decades to trace those cosmic rays
才lF它那o法想像的恐怖死亡之面
back to a death of unimaginable violence.
赫斯在W地利上空lF的宇宙射
The cosmic rays that Victor Hess detected
向科W家提出了一i
in the skies above Austria posed a mystery to scientists.
地球上的放射性V物|
Radioactivity in minerals on Earth--
比如
like uranium ore--
它的放射性碜造对子的裂
comes from the disintegration of atoms.
但宇宙射具有不同的性|
But cosmic rays were of a different nature.
它的能量更大
They were far more powerful
比r赫斯的世界中任何一N已知物|都要
than anything known in Hess's world.
科W家探索了20年
Scientists wondered for two decades
想要知道是什N|西a生了宇宙射
what could possibly produce cosmic rays.
下面介B弗Y茨?威基
Enter Fritz Zwicky,
一你]f^的最明的人
the most brilliant man you've never heard of.
1933年 他和一同事lF
In 1933, he and a colleague discovered
某些a星突然得非常耀眼
that some stars flare up to become as bright
亮度就和它所在的星系差不多K延m好字
as their entire galaxy for a few weeks,
然後又黯淡下
before fading out again.
弗Y茨?威基是世界上第一
Fritz Zwicky was the first person
t解@F象的人
to understand what just happened.
他正_的推y出
He correctly surmised that this is the way
@代表著一w大|量a星的死亡
a massive star dies-- it blows
爆炸a星的物|入太空
its guts out into space.
他把@Na星的死亡Q"超新星"
He called this kind of stellar death a "supernova"...
K推y@w垂死的a星坍s
and predicted that the dying star would shrink
100f英里的直绞湛s10英里
from about a million miles across to only ten.
a星的骸密度如此之大
This corpse would be so dense
一粒米那N大的物|
that a single grain of it would weigh as much
就和埃及大金字塔一又
as the Great Pyramid in Egypt.
它缀跤
It would consist almost entirely
一N叫中子的原子粒子M成
of subatomic particles called neutrons,
所以他也⑦@N奇的物wQ"中子星"
so he named these bizarre objects "neutron stars."
自钠威基Ay@F象存在後的35年
And 35 years after Zwicky predicted their existence,
天文W家_始找到它
astronomers began to find them.
我⑺Q"}n星"
We call them "pulsars"
它在快速自D的同rl射出有律的}n波信
when they spin rapidly and emit regular pulses of radio energy.
超新星c中子星都能l出
Supernovas and neutron stars could account
大量的宇宙射
for a wide range of cosmic rays,
但不是能量最的那N
but not the most energetic ones.
F在的科W不能很好解@NF象
Nothing yet known to science
不^]事
can explain them, and we're fine with that.
@就是我劭W的原因之一
It's one of the things I love about science,
我牟患傺b自己知道所有的答案
we don't have to pretend we have all the answers.
威基J
Zwicky also came up with the idea
星系的重力它四周的空gYl生曲
that the gravity of a galaxy warps the fabric
就像放大R一
of space around it, to act like a lens.
亩在它後面的其它星系的光
This distorts and magnifies light
在穿^@星系rl生扭曲K放大的效
from any other galaxy lying directly behind it.
因此地球上的天文W家在^y 具有相同距x的bh星系r
So, astronomers on Earth would see multiple images
看到有多重D像出F
of that same distant galaxy,
就好像[@的哈哈R效果
deformed, as in a funhouse mirror.
他做出@一Ay40年後 人才_始lF@一F象真存在
40 years after this prediction, we started finding them, too.
威基在1930年代有另一lF
And Zwicky made yet another discovery back in the 1930s.
在^y後l座星系Fr
While studying the Coma Cluster of galaxies,
他注意到星F的移臃绞胶苡幸馑
he noticed something funny about the way they moved.
它的移铀俣群芸
The galaxies were going way too fast,
在@N快的速度下 @星F早就w散了
so fast that they should've been flying apart from each other,
因樵谒有@些星系中的a星
because all the stars in all those galaxies
它的引力太小 o法SM整星F的定
had far too little gravity to hold the cluster together.
威基J
Zwicky thought
一定有某N力量⑺SM在一起
that something else must be binding them to each other.
@看不找不著的神秘部分
That mysterious missing component
它的重量至少是星F中所有的a星重的
would have to weigh something like 50 times as much
50倍以上
as the stars themselves.
但]人λ的超前解感d趣
But no one paid much attention to this wild notion.
J槟遣贿^是威基的又一狂的想法
Just another one of Zwicky's crazy ideas.
在我的太系
In our solar system,
位於热Φ男行撬星 它的移铀俣
the innermost planet, Mercury, moves much faster
要比最外圈的行星海王星快S多
than the outermost one, Neptune.
上去@很理成章 Σ
And that makes sense, right?
你越是用力推拉一物w 它的速度也就越快
The harder you push or pull on something, the faster it goes.
太的引力S距x的增加而p弱
The Sun's gravity weakens with increasing distance,
因此 距x太更h的行星移拥酶慢
so, the planets that are farther from the Sun move more slowly.
人J樾窍底钔拥a星
Everyone expected that the outermost stars in a galaxy
也是@右拥
would act the same way.
大部分的a星都向著星系的中心集中
Most of the stars are concentrated towards the center,
因此 它的重力和恳其它的a星
so, their collective gravity pulls on the other stars
如同太恳行星一
the same way the Sun pulls on the planets.
可是在1970年
But in the 1970s, when astronomer
天文W家S拉・e在研究M女座星系r
Vera Rubin studied the Andromeda Galaxy,
她lF@星系的外a星K]有遵循@律
she discovered that the outer stars obeyed no such rule.
它c太系的外有行遣灰
Unlike the outer planets of the solar system,
星系外a星的速度
the outer stars in the galaxy were all going at the same speed
c星系a星的速度是一拥
as the stars that were closer in,
它移拥蒙踔帘热A想中的要快
and they were moving way faster than expected.
"太有意思了" S拉想道
"That's funny," Vera thought.
"M女座星系里一定有古怪"
"There must be something weird about the Andromeda Galaxy."
於是 她又^y另一星系
So she looked at another galaxy.
lF了同拥默F象
Same story.
再下一 也是如此
And another.
S拉一共^y了60星系
Vera studied 60 galaxies
lF所有的星系
and found that all of them
似乎都`背了f有引力定律
seemed to be violating the Law of Gravity,
@是物理W中的核心理
a core principle of physics.
一_始 她的同事@F象表示|疑
After some initial healthy skepticism,
S後他_始邮肿约河^y
her colleagues looked for themselves,
Y果lFS拉的^yY果是正_的
and found that Vera was right.
但K非是牛D的f有引力定律有}
It's not that Isaac Newton had gotten the Law of Gravity wrong;
而是S拉・elF了
Vera Rubin had discovered that the gravity
某N巨大而又不可的引力
of something massive and invisible
在迫使星星移蛹涌
was forcing the stars to go fast.
然後 有人想起了狂的老威基的f法
And then, someone remembered crazy old Fritz Zwicky,
那不明碓吹囊力
and the unknown source of gravity
肯定是存在於星系F中
in the galaxy clusters
1933年的r候 他就⑵浞Q之"暗物|"
that he called "dark matter," back in 1933.
S拉・eC了
Vera Rubin had verified the existence
一全新的 更|的宇宙的存在
of a new, much larger cosmos.
它c我^去以楹懿t解的那宇宙一
And just like the one we thought we knew,
充M了W秘
it was filled with mystery.
暗物|完全是探y不到的
Dark matter is completely unobservable,
但它a生引力效
except for its gravitational effect,
@加速可的a星c星系的移铀俣
which makes visible stars and galaxies move faster.
它的性|同邮且i
Its nature is another deep mystery.
e提供的C表明 @不可的宇宙
Rubin had provided the evidence for an invisible universe
比我已知的宇宙要大10倍以上
nearly ten times more massive than the one we thought we knew.
就好比暗夜Y站在海的人
It was as if we had been standing on the seashore
e`地J
at night, mistakenly believing
海浪上的小泡沫 就是大海的全部
that the froth on the waves was all there was to the ocean.
S拉・e^ya星r意R到了
Vera Rubin looked at the stars and realized
眼前的星星只不^是海浪上的小泡沫
they were merely the foam on the waves,
海洋最验的部分 不被人知
and that the greatest part of the ocean remained unknown.
且慢
But wait.
@得越碓蒋狂了
It gets crazier.
我的y河系
Our Milky Way Galaxy,
有蛋|wa星
a few hundred billion stars,
有o档男请cm埃
plus the clouds of gas and dust,
那些|西^去曾是 未硪再a星
the stuff of once and future stars--
宇宙中有上百|其它星系--所有@些
and about a hundred billion other galaxies-- all of that,
再加上]yM去的
including those uncounted billions of trillions
狄|兆的行星 l星和彗星
of planets, moons, and comets--
它的和只不^是@宇宙的百分之五
amounts to only five percent of what is actually there.
因橛更大的未解之i
Because there's a bigger unsolved mystery
比暗物|更神秘
than dark matter--
那就是暗能量
dark energy, which makes up even more of the cosmos
它著大部分的宇宙K又它的膨
and drives its expansion.
弗Y茨?威基lF的超新星
And it was Fritz Zwicky's supernovas
槿祟揭示了一l@示其存在的途
that lit the way to the revelation of its existence.
e例子 一wa星耗M了它所有的核燃料後
In one scenario, a star consumes all of its nuclear fuel...
它先是冷s下
then cools,
然後在自身引力的作用下突然塌s
and suddenly collapses under its own gravity.
S後在聚的反作用力下a星l生巨大的爆炸
The star rebounds in a massive explosion,
最後只z留下一w中子星或是一黑洞
leaving behind a neutron star or a black hole.
由於爆l前那wa星的|量
Since the mass of the original star
上下浮拥^g很大
can fall within a wide range,
它槌新星後的峰值亮度
its peak brightness as a supernova
也有很大的不同
can also vary widely.
因此我不能牧炼砼
So, you can't tell how far away it is
@w星星x我有多h
just from how bright it looks.
一w^近的超新星亮度看起硪苍S就和在^h地方
A relatively nearby supernova
爆l的超新星差不多 就算另一w的爆l度更大
might appear just as bright as one that was more powerful, but farther away.
但有另外一N超新星
But there's another kind of supernova
它只有一N爆l度
that comes in only one strength.
它看上去彷肪褪羌ち业奶礁晡杞K曲r
It marks the violent grand finale
一wt巨星c一wt矮星翩翩共舞的宏大鼍
of a tango danced by a giant star and a dwarf.
@深w星的\行道互相接近r
As the two stars orbit closely around each other,
t巨星外拥怏wAa而出
the giant sheds its outer layers of gas
流到t矮星上
onto the dwarf.
t矮星增加的重量
When the added weight becomes too much
超^了它所能承受的O限r
for it to bear,
星w就像一w巨大的核炸一颖炸
the dwarf detonates like a stupendous thermonuclear bomb.
有持m好字艿rg
For a few weeks,
天空中@w超新星的亮度
the brilliance of such a supernova rivals
超^它的星系中其他a星亮度的和
the combined light of all the stars in its galaxy.
@N型的超新星
This kind of supernova
它出的最大能量值是相同的
always has the same maximum power output,
它大s比太亮50|倍
about five billion times brighter than our Sun.
通^巨大的天文望hR
With big telescopes,
我可以在非常bh的星系中看到它
we can see them in galaxies very far away,
即使它就位於可^y宇宙的
out toward the edge of the observable universe.
因樗有@N型的超新星具有相同的亮度
Because all such supernovas have the same wattage,
因此 它是用於y量距x的理想工具
they're ideal tools for measuring distances
m用於宇宙中哪怕是最bh的星系
to the farthest reaches of the universe.
我也Q之"T光"
We call them "standard candles."
1929年 埃德?哈勃lF宇宙正在膨
In 1929, Edwin Hubble discovered that the universe is expanding.
bh的星系正在hx彼此
The distant galaxies are drifting away from one another.
後砦知道了
Later, we learned
宇宙的膨始於140|年前
that the expansion began some 14 billion years ago
"宇宙大爆炸" _始的那一刻起
with the explosive birth of the universe-- the big bang.
人曾以
Everybody assumed
宇宙的膨速度慢下
that the rate of expansion would be slowing down,
@是由於宇宙各部分之g的引力
due to the mutual pull of gravity
互相恳的Y果
between all the parts of the universe.
如果有足蚨嗟陌滴镔|
If there is enough dark matter,
它的引力最K⒂钪娴呐蛎停止下
its gravity would eventually bring the expansion to a stop,
宇宙又s回到原c
and the universe would then fall back on itself.
照@油评 宇宙中的f物K究在
In that case, everything would eventually collapse
一次大D褐腥面崩
in a big crunch.
但反^碚f 如果宇宙中的暗物|再少一些
On the other hand, if the universe had less dark matter,
宇宙的膨就永h^m下去
the expansion would continue forever,
只是速度越碓铰
just getting slower and slower.
芍Щハ喔的天文W家F
Two competing teams of astronomers
同r在^y著bh星系中的@些超新星
were observing those supernovas in distant galaxies.
@可以f是另一
It turned out to be another one
"有意思"的r刻
of those "that's funny" moments.
1998年 @呻b立的研究F
In 1998, both teams independently came
做出了同拥慕Y
to the same conclusion.
宇宙的膨不H]有p
The expansion isn't slowing down at all...
而且在不停的加速
it's speeding up.
@意味著宇宙永h膨下去
This means the universe will continue to expand forever.
宇宙中似乎有一股神秘的力量
There seems to be a mysterious force in the universe,
它的模大得足以旱挂磺幸力
one that overwhelms gravity on the grandest scale
⒂钪娣珠_
to push the cosmos apart.
宇宙中大部分的能量
Most of the energy of the universe is bound up
都被@股看不的力量束`著
in this unknown force.
我Q之"暗能量"
We call it "dark energy,"
可@名字就和"暗物|"一
but that name, like "dark matter,"
我不知道它是什N 只能o它起名字而已
is merely a code word for our ignorance.
我承J不知道所有}的答案
It's okay not to know all the answers.
承J自己的o知
It's better to admit our ignorance
比行J可那些可能e`的答案好
than to believe answers that might be wrong.
假b自己什N都懂 就是P上了
Pretending to know everything closes the door
通往真相的大T
to finding out what's really there.
今晚 我的w船航行到了
Tonight, our ships sail
更奇的水域
into even more exotic waters.
跟我
Come with me.
人只有伤绎w船冒UM入了
Only two of our ships have ventured
星H空g中的黑暗大洋
into the great dark ocean of interstellar space.
@是史上最L的冒U之旅
The longest odyssey in all of history
它_始於1977年
was launched back in 1977--
美宇航局的旅行者1c旅行者2
NASA's Voyager 1 and 2.
@伤绎w船以每小r4f英里的速度行M
The Voyagers move about 40,000 miles an hour.
它人得以第一次近距x^察
They gave us our first close-up look
木星上的大t斑
at Jupiter's Great Red Spot,
那是比地球的尺寸要大三倍的ZL
a hurricane three times the size of Earth
其中一ZL至少在1644年就已_始刮起
and one that's been raging since at least 1644,
K第一次被人^y到
when it was first observed.
所以我知道 @些ZL至少可以延m登年
For all we know, it could be thousands of years old.
旅行者lF了 在木星的l星
The Voyagers discovered the first active volcano
木l一上有活火山的存在
on another world, on Jupiter's moon Io...
在木l二的冰酉
and an ocean beneath the icy surface
t存在著海洋
of the moon Europa...
它可能碛斜鹊厍蛑辽俣2倍的液B水
with at least twice as much water as we have here on Earth.
旅行者勇敢的w越了土星h
The Voyagers dared to fly across Saturn's rings
lF它是由狄园儆的AhЫM成
and revealed that they were made of hundreds of thin bands
而@些Aht是由小雪球M成
of orbiting snowballs.
在土星的巨大l星土l六上
On Saturn's giant moon Titan,
旅行者lF了比地球夂4倍的大
Voyager detected an atmosphere four times denser than Earth's.
暗示著在土l六上有可能存在甲烷的海洋
That hinted at the existence of hydrocarbon seas on Titan,
@一c後肀蛔C了
which we later confirmed.
旅行者2人第一次得到了
Voyager 2 gave us our first portrait
最外拥男行 海王星的肖像
of the outermost planet, Neptune...
海王星上狂L咆哮 L速_每小r1000英里
where the winds roar at 1,000 miles per hour...
在它的l星海l一上
and its moon Triton, where geysers
g歇泉能把沸v的液氮到5英里高
of boiling nitrogen shoot five miles high.
旅行者成功的完成了
Voyager successfully completed its mission of discovery
它ν有行堑挠^y任
to the outer planets,
但它M入黑暗世界的冒U之旅
but its odyssey into the darkness
才_始
was just beginning.
在l射後的35年
35 years after its launch,
旅行者1成槿祟第一
Voyager 1 became the first of our spacecraft
M入未知I域的太空w船
to enter an uncharted realm.
太向各方向不嗟匕l射出
The Sun is constantly shooting out streams
щ的粒子流
of charged particles in all directions,
粒子流的r速_100f英里
moving at a million miles an hour.
@就是太L 它U散後的^域是一巨大的磁泡
This solar wind blows a vast magnetic bubble,
形成了太L 它一直延伸到最外拥男行侵外
our heliosphere, that extends beyond the outer planets.
它把男请H空gM入的稀薄怏w向外推
It pushes out against the thin gas of interstellar space.
@就是一世界的M^ 另一世界的起c
There's a border where one ends and the other begins.
旅行者1向地球蟾嬲f
Voyager 1 reported back to Earth
它的探y器正在遭遇
that its detectors were being pummeled
越碓蕉嗟挠钪嫔渚攻
by more and more cosmic rays.
直至F在 我是不知道
Until then, we didn't know
哪Y才是浩瀚星H大洋的_始
where the interstellar ocean began.
旅行者1不嗲靶
Voyager 1 pressed on
它穿越了人奈创┰降倪界
past a boundary we had never crossed before.
太L槲阻趿舜蟛糠种旅的宇宙射
The heliosphere shields us from most of the deadly cosmic rays.
太L如E雨般爆lr
When stormy solar winds blow,
太L右S之U
this zone of protection grows;
太L平or 它s小
in calm solar weather, it shrinks.
y河系附近出F超新星爆lr
When a star goes supernova in our galactic neighborhood...
爆l後的星w骸
the debris from the exploded star
⑻L油葡蛱的方向
pushes the heliosphere back towards the Sun.
如果骸的能量足虼
If it's strong enough to push it
它就有可能M入地球的道
all the way back to Earth's orbit,
我的星球就沐浴在具有射性的超新星骸中
our planet gets a radioactive bath of supernova debris.
好在@拥那r不常l生
Luckily, this doesn't happen very often.
最後一次出F是在200f年前
The last one was perhaps two million years ago.
近的一wa星爆l了
A neighboring star explodes a million years
地球上要再^100f年才出F人@物N
before there's even such a thing as the human species.
我暮蔚弥此事
How can we possibly know this?
因樗劳龅a星留下E
Because the dying star left its traces
它就藏在海洋下子⒗锾
miles below the surface of the ocean.
@是iY核 就像@K小石^
Manganese nodules, small rocks like this one,
它分散在深海的海床上
are scattered over much of the deep sea floor.
它的生L速度非常慢
They grow very slowly.
100f年才能L1毫米
I'm talking a millimeter in a million years,
一拥亩询B生L
layer upon layer.
iY核c菌共生
These nodules grow in partnership with bacteria
它吸取溶解在海水中的V物|
by taking up minerals dissolved in the seawater.
超新星a生一N具有放射性的F
A supernova produces a radioactive form of iron,
它和地球上自然a生的任何一N物|都不一
unlike anything made by natural processes on Earth.
研究人TlF了@NF的痕E
Researchers found telltale traces of this iron
它就L在iY核中
in a thin layer below the surface
外は碌囊\友Y
of the manganese nodules.
研究人T把已知的iY核的生L速率
They used the known rate of growth of the nodules
和每拥纳LrgM起
to date that layer and to connect it
就能知道|f年前a星缤龅拿\了
to the fate of a star that perished eons ago.
你看到的是石^
The difference between seeing nothing but a pebble
但在科W家眼Y @是深藏在Y面的宇宙的v史
and reading the history of the cosmos inscribed inside it
@就是科W的力量
is science.
星H大洋黑暗而深h
The interstellar ocean is dark and deep.
哪茄Y看 太只不^是天空中一w最亮的a星
Out here, the Sun is just the brightest star in the sky.
旅行者依然保持著
Yet the Voyagers maintain their regular communications
c美宇航局馔七M室定期的M
with NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory,
他的交流要^1光r
talking back and forth across the light-hours
@就是太空船c母港之g的距x
that separate these ships from their home port.
再]有人造的物w
No other objects touched by human hands
曾如此冒Uhx家@
have ever ventured this far from home.
@些w船
Even after they lose their ability
失去了c人通的能力之後
to respond to our command,
旅行者最後一也是最L的一任
the last and, by far, the longest phase
就此拉_序幕
of the Voyager mission will begin.
1979年 旅行者@著木星旋Dr
Back in 1979, when both Voyagers rounded Jupiter,
木星的巨大引力就像一弓
its massive gravity acted as a slingshot,
把它出太系
flinging them out of the solar system
它得以在y河系的a星g航行
to travel among the stars of our galaxy
rg是10|年
for a billion years.
年 卡?_根意R到旅行者的任
Carl Sagan recognized that the Voyager mission
槿祟提供了接近永a的C票
offered two free tickets to something approaching eternity.
他M建了一小 造了一些信息
He assembled a small team to create a message
以便在未淼哪骋惶
to any civilization that might, one day,
某文明遇到@U的航天器r可以x到它
encounter the derelict spacecraft.
26世o前
26 centuries ago,
述王以撒哈D道
the Assyrian king Esarhaddon wrote...
"朕以青~T碑
"I had monuments made of bronze
文於泥版
and inscriptions of baked clay.
z之於基石 髦於後世"
I left them in the foundations for future times."
@些象形D形延m了@一古老的鹘y
These hieroglyphics continue that ancient tradition.
它被刻印在w子上 上面的信息被O成
They are inscribed on the cover of a message designed
方便其它世界或後世的生物x
to be read by the beings of other worlds and times.
我人c外星文明之g
What could we possibly have in common
有可能有什N共同c呢
with an alien civilization
他有自己c不同的M化史
with its own separate evolutionary history
甚至有可能比我更先M
and one so far advanced beyond us
能自由遨[於星H空g
that they can patrol interstellar space?
但至少有一|西
One thing at least,
是宇宙g通用的Z言
a universal language...
科W
science.
引力的束`是很y被打破的
It's hard to break the bonds of gravity.
想要在宇宙之海中尺[
You can only sail the cosmic seas
你必通Wc物理
if you speak mathematics and physics.
涫怯钪嬷凶畛Ｒ的元素
Hydrogen is the most common element in the universe.
湓子中的子
The electron in a hydrogen atom
在它的旋D方向上作翻D\
flips the direction of its spin
它的速率或l率是a定的
at a constant rate, or frequency.
湓子就像是迷你的天然r
Hydrogen atoms are like tiny natural clocks--
滴…答…走
tick... tock.
@就意味著我c外星人共同碛
Now we have a unit of time in common
相同的一rg挝
with the extraterrestrials.
t解了@
This will come in handy when we get to the next level
再D到下一信息r就好理解了
of the message.
下面的信息是指示出我在宇宙中的位置
Here's our return address in space.
}n星是快速旋D的中子星
Pulsars are rapidly-spinning neutron stars
它l出定期爆l的o波
that give off regular bursts of radio waves.
你可以根@碓O定rg
You can set your clock by them.
太位於@示意D的中心
The Sun is at the center of this diagram,
@些l指向14w最近的}n星
and the lines point to the 14 nearest pulsars.
有一蔚嘶`指示出了每w}n星的特有l率
A simple code labels each pulsar with its unique frequency,
K用湓子
using the ticktock of the hydrogen atom
作橛r挝
as the unit of time.
因此 外星的天文W家能利用@示意D
So alien astronomers could use this diagram
矶ㄎ怀雎眯姓咛航天器的母星
to locate the home star of the Voyager spacecraft
在我y河系中的位置
in our galaxy.
他能知道
They could also tell
@艘航天器已l射多久了
how long ago the spacecraft was launched.
@一c很重要
And that's important because the Voyager record
因槁眯姓咛的外ぴO勖是10|年
has a projected shelf life of 1,000 million years.
就想像一下你是一
Become an extraterrestrial archaeologist
外星球的考古W家
for a few moments.
有一架人造航天器完成了它在星H大洋中的使命
An artifact has been fished out of the interstellar ocean.
它是由外星智慧生命
It was made by beings
在10|年前建造的
that lived about a billion years ago.
你要怎油ㄟ^它t解他和他的世界
What would you make of them and their world?
他o我送砹怂的音
They've sent us their music
有用59N人Z言f出的候方式
and greetings in 59 human languages.
@是地球上一位小孩子向你打招呼
Hello from the children of planet Earth.
L~的Z言
And one whale language.
有一串音的M合 包括土星五火箭l射的音
And a sound essay that includes a Saturn V rocket launch.
一位母Hλ新生的赫f的
A mother's first words to her newborn baby.
哦 戆
Oh, come on now.
做好孩子…做好孩子
Be a good boy... be a good boy.
一位入酆拥哪贻p女子的X波
The brain waves of a young woman newly fallen in love.
有}n星的音
And the sound of a pulsar.
所有@些都能存在10|年之久
All of that will live for a billion years.
10|年有多久
How long is a billion years?
如果你能把世大爆炸以淼rg
If you compress all the time since the Big Bang,
也就是宇宙Q生的那一刻_始的rg
the explosive birth of the universe,
嚎s成一地球年的
into a single Earth year,
10|年就相於@1年中的1月
a billion years is about one month of that year.
10|年前的地球上l生了些什N
What was happening on Earth a billion years ago?
大部分的地球地都聚集在一超大上
Most of Earth's land was amassed into a supercontinent
我Q之榱_迪尼大
called Rodinia.
@是一荒地 ]有游 ]有植物
It was a barren desert-- no animals, no plants.
10|年前
A billion years ago, there wasn't enough oxygen
空庋Y]有足虻难跻孕纬沙粞
in our atmosphere to form an ozone layer,
]有它的保o
and without it, ultraviolet radiation
紫外阻止生命在地上生存
prevented life from colonizing the land.
_迪尼大看上去可能更像火星
Rodinia probably looked more like Mars
而不像今天的地球
than present-day Earth.
巨大的海洋世界a生大暴雨
The giant world ocean produced huge rainstorms
造成洪水和侵g
causing flooding and erosion.
冰川形成 它慢而o情的\又
Glaciers formed, and their slow but relentless movements
把地塑造成新的幼
carved the land into new shapes.
渭胞的生物主宰著海洋
Single-celled organisms dominated the oceans,
被Q"微生物席"的生物集群地已_始出F
but some existed in colonies called "microbial mats,"
第一多胞生物很快演形成
and the first multicellular organisms would soon evolve.
10|年後
And a billion years from now,
今天的地球又成怎印
what will Earth be like...
我的城市 埃及的金字塔
long after our cities, the Egyptian pyramids,
洛基山} 是否早已被侵gm土
the Rocky Mountains have all been eroded to dust?
於@N久h的rg碚f
There are few things we can say with confidence
我]有准事是可以f得清的
about such a far distant time.
我唯一可以肯定的是
The only thing we can say for sure
我所JR的地球l生巨
is that Earth as we know it will be so changed
缀]有人J得出 @曾是我的家@
that we would scarcely recognize it as home.
但就算是10|年後
But even a thousand million years from now,
我人的本性
something of who we were and the music that we made
和我在久h的春天下的音
in that long-ago spring...
都延m下去
will live on.
在如此bh的未 我的太系
In that distant future, our Sun will have completed
完成了@著y河系中心公D4圈的v程
another four orbits around the center of the galaxy...
旅行者早已w到了hx太的I域
...and the Voyagers will have ventured far from the Sun.
卡?_根曾是旅行者影像小M的一T
Carl Sagan was a member of Voyager's imaging team,
旅行者拍z的最後一照片碜造端的想法
and it was his idea that Voyager take one last picture.
在一代人以前
A generation before,
阿波_登月w行的最後一位宇航T
an astronaut on the last Apollo flight to the Moon
照下了一地球的全景照片
had taken a picture of the whole Earth--
@是一]有界的行星
the planet as a world without borders.
它成了一N新意R的象徵
It became an icon of a new consciousness.
卡F了@^程的下一步
Carl realized the next step in this process.
他f服了美宇航局把旅行者一的R^
He convinced NASA to turn the Voyager 1 camera
在w^海王星r D回地球
back towards Earth when the spacecraft went beyond Neptune
它最後看一眼家@ 他所f的那
for one last look homeward at what he called...
泛著n白the pale blue dot.
在那Y
That's here.
那是家@
That's home.
那是我
That's us.
在那Y 你鄣拿人
On it, everyone you love,
你JR的每人
everyone you know,
你f^的每人
everyone you ever heard of,
在@世上存在^的每人
every human being who ever was,
度^了自己的一生
lived out their lives.
聚集在@Y的 是我的g泛屯纯
The aggregate of our joy and suffering,
是成千上f的宗教信仰 意R形B
thousands of confident religions, ideologies,
和Wf
and economic doctrines,
每C手c食者
every hunter and forager,
每英雄c懦夫
every hero and coward,
每文明的立者和缯
every creator and destroyer of civilization,
每王cr夫
every king and peasant,
每δ贻p的H
every young couple in love,
每一母Hc父H 充M希望的孩子
every mother and father, hopeful child,
l明家c探U家
inventor and explorer,
每一位高尚的教 每一位腐的政客
every teacher of morals, every corrupt politician,
每一位超明星 每一位最高I袖
every superstar, every supreme leader,
人史上的每一位}人和罪人
every saint and sinner in the history of our species,
都生活在@Y
lived there...
如一粒微m
on a mote of dust
腋≡谝皇光之中
suspended... in a sunbeam.
地球是在浩瀚的宇宙背景下的
The Earth is a very small stage
一很小的舞台
in a vast, cosmic arena.
想想^去的血流成河
Think of the rivers of blood
那榈弁⑾喽流的血
spilled by all those generals and emperors
只樽他在光s和倮中
so that in glory and triumph
成樗查g的ト
they could become the momentary masters
子心且小c中…那一小部分
of a fraction... of a dot.
想想那oM的酷
Think of the endless cruelties visited
D像Y那一像素c的某角落的民
by the inhabitants of one corner of this pixel
每天把@酷施加到c他]什N^e的
on the scarcely distinguishable inhabitants
另一角落的民身上
of some other corner.
他楹纬３Ｕ`解
How frequent their misunderstandings,
他楹慰释⑺Ψ
how eager they are to kill one another,
他的憎恨楹稳绱丝
how fervent their hatreds.
我在b模做
Our posturings,
我自以楹苤匾
our imagined self-importance,
妄想著我人地位特殊
the delusion that we have some privileged position
在宇宙中c不同
in the universe,
@一切 都因@泛著n白are challenged by this point of pale light.
我的星球
Our planet...
不^是一粒孤的微m
is a lonely speck in the great,
\罩在ゴ蟮挠钪婧诎抵中
enveloping cosmic dark.
我默默o
In our obscurity,
沉浸在oM的浩瀚Y
in all this vastness,
]有一z索@示 除了我自己
there is no hint that help will come from elsewhere
有l能拯救我
to save us from ourselves.
地球是目前已知唯一有生命的世界
The Earth is the only world known so far to harbor life.
生命再o其他去
There is nowhere else,
至少在不久的 亦是如此
at least in the near future,
]有外星球 供人w移
to which our species could migrate.
只可⒂^
Visit, yes.
不能定居
Settle, not yet.
不管你喜gc否
Like it or not,
F在 只有地球供我立足
for the moment, the Earth is where we make our stand.
f研天文 可以人t卑
It has been said that astronomy is a humbling
塑造人心 磨性
and character-building experience.
也S再]有更好的方法
There is perhaps no better demonstration
能比@bh的面
of the folly of human conceits
更好地@示出人的自c愚蠢
than this distant image.
ξ叶言 它To me, it underscores our responsibility
要θ烁友善
to deal more kindly with one another
懂得珍惜c圩o
and to preserve and cherish
@泛著n白the pale blue dot,
是我知道的唯一的家@
the only home we've ever known.
我是如何
How did we,
在@一粒微m上居住的渺小生物
tiny creatures living on that speck of dust,
是如何千方百地把宇宙w船
ever manage to figure out how to send spacecraft
送入y河的星星之g
out among the stars of the Milky Way?
就在装倌昵 也就是宇宙v中的酌rg
Only a few centuries ago, a mere second of cosmic time,
我尚不知道自己身在何方 r楹r
we knew nothing of where or when we were.
τ钪娴钠渌部分一o所知
Oblivious to the rest of the cosmos,
我身居囚\
we inhabited a kind of prison--
活在自己的小宇宙Y
a tiny universe
困在ぶ中
bounded by a nutshell.
我是如何逃出囚\
How did we escape from the prison?
是因槭朗来代探索者的不懈努力
It was the work of generations of searchers
他l自刃牡刈5l我t
who took five simple rules to heart.
|疑嗤
Question authority.
不p信人言
No idea is true just because someone says so,
包括自己在
including me.
立思考
Think for yourself.
自我|疑
Question yourself.
不因自己想要相信 而相信任何事情
Don't believe anything just because you want to.
相信不代表能成楝F
Believing something doesn't make it so.
依靠^察c
Test ideas by the evidence gained
以Cz想法
from observation and experiment.
如果自己喜g的想法]有通^全面的z
If a favorite idea fails a well-designed test,
它就是e的
it's wrong!
酚^一c
Get over it.
遵循C o它指向哪Y
Follow the evidence, wherever it leads.
如果]有C 不妄下定
If you have no evidence, reserve judgment.
也S最重要的t就是
And perhaps the most important rule of all...
要住 你也犯e
Remember, you could be wrong.
即使是最秀的科W家
Even the best scientists
也曾在某些事情上犯e
have been wrong about some things.
牛D 垡蛩固
Newton, Einstein,
有v史上每一位ゴ蟮目W家
and every other great scientist in history,
他都犯^e
they all made mistakes.
@很正常 是人都犯e
Of course they did-- they were human.
科W我不再欺_自己
Science is a way to keep from fooling ourselves...
欺_e人
and each other.
科W家有罪
Have scientists known sin?
有的
Of course.
我曾E用科W
We have misused science, just as we have
就像手的工具一与S意使用
every other tool at our disposal,
因此我不能把科W
and that's why we can't afford
放在少档恼嗾呤种
to leave it in the hands of a powerful few.
科W更多的凫度人r
The more science belongs to all of us,
它就越不被y用
the less likely it is to be misused.
科W的r值能阻止
These values undermine the appeals
狂崤co知
of fanaticism and ignorance
竟
and, after all,
宇宙的大部分是黑暗的
the universe is mostly dark,
只有cc的星光cY著
dotted by islands of light.
t解了地球的年g a星的距x
Learning the age of the Earth or the distance to the stars
生命的演
or how life evolves--
@世界有什N^e
what difference does that make?
嗯 @取Q於
Well, part of it depends on how big a universe
你意生活在多大的宇宙Y
you're willing to live in.
有些人喜g小宇宙
Some of us like it small.
]PS
That's fine.
完全可以理解
Understandable.
但我喜g大的宇宙
But I like it big.
我把@一切放在我的心Y 我的X海Y
And when I take all of this into my heart and my mind,
我感到心情振^
I'm uplifted by it.
@N感X涌起 我希望看到它是真的
And when I have that feeling, I want to know that it's real,
而不HH是我X海中的想像
that it's not just something happening inside my own head,
因檫@就是真相
because it matters what's true,
而我的想像
and our imagination is nothing
c自然中令人@@的F相比 根本不算什N
compared with Nature's awesome reality.
我想要知道 在那黑暗的地方有什N
I want to know what's in those dark places,
在世大爆炸之前l生了什N
and what happened before the Big Bang.
我想要知道 在宇宙的界之外是什N
I want to know what lies beyond the cosmic horizon,
生命又是如何起源的
and how life began.
宇宙中有]有地方
Are there other places in the cosmos
物|和能量在那Y被x予
where matter and energy have become alive...
生命和意R
and aware?
我想要t解我的先祖
I want to know my ancestors--
t解他每一人
all of them.
我想要成橐美好而大的接
I want to be a good, strong link
M世世代代的人
in the chain of generations.
我想要保o我的孩子
I want to protect my children
以及未淼淖O後代
and the children of ages to come.
我 代表著宇宙在@世界的耳目
We, who embody the local eyes and ears
代表著宇宙在@世界的想法c情感
and thoughts and feelings of the cosmos,
我_始t解人的起源
we've begun to learn the story of our origins--
思考繁星的故事 物|的演化
star stuff contemplating the evolution of matter,
追溯意R起源之前那l漫L的道路
tracing that long path by which it arrived at consciousness.
我c@星球上的其他生物
We and the other living things on this planet
yе宇宙M化的za
carry a legacy of cosmic evolution
逾越了凳|年
spanning billions of years.
如果我⑦@些知R於心
If we take that knowledge to heart,
如果我t解K鄞笞匀坏谋举|
if we come to know and love nature as it really is,
我的子O一定住我
then we will surely be remembered by our descendants
因槲是生命之中美好而大的一h
as good, strong links in the chain of life.
我的子O也^m@神}的探索
And our children will continue this sacred searching,
薪火相 不嚅_拓
seeing for us as we have seen for those who came before,
就在@宇宙之中 lF我做
discovering wonders yet undreamt of...
都想不到的奇E
in the cosmos.
■
在u作@部o片的字幕的^程中
越碓桨lF人的渺小至O
世界永h超出我所想像的
括而言 智慧 勇 倔 都是科研人T必碛械奶刭|
而@部o片最後的那一段
也向大家作出了在科W世界探索的五大要素
@部o片比你本上W到的|西要多
管今天我o法l掘到宇宙的全部W妙
希望@部o片能蚣ぐl你
相信某一天 坐在幕前的你 特e是年p的你
在未能槲解_iF 槿祟l展揭_全新的一